Guide to the Office of the Registrar school registers 1892-1919
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Office of the Registrar school registers
1892-1919
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
Archives 354
Washington State Agricultural College and School of Science.
9 Linear feet of shelf space 17 boxes
The collection contains school registers, or student registers, from the first (1892) enrollees at what would become Washington State University up through 1919.
Washington State University was founded as the Washington Agricultural College and School of Science in 1890, and became the State College of Washington (colloquially Washington State College) in 1905. It enrolled its first students and began instruction in January of 1892. During its early years the school offered both college courses and non-college courses, the most common non-college program was the Preparatory School, later the Elementary School or Elementary Science program, which was the equivalent of today's high school education.
The Office of the Registrar is responsible for handling student records; the role of the registrar dates to the earliest days of the campus, though the first registrar also served a secretarial role. Today it's responsible for virtually all non-medical student data.
The collection contains school registers, or student registers, from the first (1892) enrollees at what would become Washington State University up through 1919. In 1905, the volumes began including summer school enrollment information. They include the school's college students and non-college students both. The content of the registers varies over time, but consists of student information that can include attendance, grades, limited demographic information, and notes on why they finally left the school. The collection is retained in its original bindings and order.
The collection is broken into two series of registers. The first series is defined as college registers, but the first several volumes, at least, clearly contain non-college enrollees. It is unclear if later volumes also do. The second, smaller series is identified as Preparatory School students.
The first three volumes of series one and all four volumes of series two list students, loosely, by when they enrolled, and then records multiple years' work under their name. These volumes include a student index at the front. The other volumes list all students enrolled in a given year and then their work for that year. These volumes are generally mostly alphabetical, though there may be multiple series within a given volume: in some cases each semester is separate, and in some cases students are separated by program. As a result of the differing systems for recording data, there may be some overlap between the two types of volumes, and those interested in students in those years will need to check multiple volumes.
This collection is open and available for research use.
The materials in this collection, along with a variety of statistical reports and some Regents Minutes, were given to MASC by Dave Guzman of the Washington State University Registrar's Office on June 17, 1996, and retained as accession UA1996-12.
The Office of the Registrar materials separated from these registers can be found in Archives 353 (Office of the Registrar Reports, 1917-1974) and in Archives 257 (Board of Regents Minutes, 1891-1998). MASC holds similar records from 1920 to 1940 as accession UA1995-06, but due to FERPA regulations those materials remain sealed against use until the deaths of those students.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Washington State Agricultural College and School of Science -- Registers.; State College of Washington -- Registers.; Washington State University -- Registers.; State College of Washington.; Washington State University.
Colleges and Universities; Washington (State)
- Series 1: "College"
  - Admitted 1892 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Admitted 1892-1897 (Box 1, Volume 2)
  - Admitted 1896-1898 (Box 2, Volume 3)
  - 1895-1896 and 1896-1897 (Box 3, Volume 4)
  - 1897-1898 and 1898-1899 (Box 3, Volume 5)
  - 1899-1900 and 1900-1901 (Box 3, Volume 6)
  - 1901-1902 and 1902-1903 (Box 4, Volume 7)
  - 1903-1904 and 1904-1905. Begins including Summer school with 1905. (Box 4, Volume 8)
  - 1905-1906 (Box 5, Volume 9)
  - 1906-1907 v.1 (Box 5, Volume 10)
  - 1906-1907 v.2 (Box 5, Volume 11)
  - 1907-1908 v.1 (Box 6, Volume 12)
  - 1907-1908 v.2 (Box 6, Volume 13)
  - 1908-09 (Box 6, Volume 14)
  - 1909-1910 and 1910-1911 (Box 7, Volume 15)
  - 1911-1912 (Box 8, Volume 16)
  - 1912-1913 (Box 9, Volume 17)
  - 1913-1914 (Box 10, Volume 18)
  - 1914-1915 (Box 11, Volume 19)
  - 1915-1916 (Box 12, Volume 20)
  - 1916-1917 v.1 (Box 13, Volume 21)
  - 1916-1917 v.2 (Box 14, Volume 22)
  - 1917-1918 (Box 15, Volume 23)
  - 1918-1919 (Box 16, Volume 24)
- Series 2: Preparatory School
  - Admitted 1892-1895 (Box 17, Volume 25)
  - Admitted 1895-1897 (Box 17, Volume 26)
  - Admitted 1897-1898 (Box 17, Volume 27)
  - Admitted 1898 (Box 17, Volume 28)